# Fabio Miranda

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE, COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING

University of Illinois at Chicago

851 S. Morgan St, MC 152, Chicago, IL, 60607

□ (+1) 347-545-6405 | **Transport** fabiom@uic.edu | **A** fmiranda.me

#### **Research Interests**

I am interested in developing techniques that allow for the interactive visual analysis of large-scale data, combining methods from visualization, data management, machine learning and computer graphics. I have worked closely with domain experts from different fields and the outcome of these collaborations included not only research published in leading venues, but also systems that were made available to experts in academia, industry and government agencies. My work has also received extensive coverage from different media outlets, including The New York Times, The Economist, Architectural Digest, Curbed, among others.

#### **Education**

2012 - 2018 Ph.D. in Computer Science

New York, NY, USA

New York University (NYU)

Advised by Professor Cláudio T. Silva, IEEE Fellow

Dissertation: "Data structures for the interactive visual analysis of urban data".

2009 - 2011 M.S. in Computer Science

Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Advised by Professor Waldemar Celes.

Thesis: "Volume rendering of unstructured hexahedral meshes".

2005 - 2009 B.S. in Computer Science

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG) Advised by Professor Luiz Chaimowicz.

# **Professional Experience**

Oct. 2020 - present University of Illinois at Chicago

Chicago, IL, USA

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering

Fall 2018 - Fall 2020 New York University

New York, NY, USA

Postdoctoral researcher

Summer 2016 Argonne National Laboratory

Lemont, IL, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Venkatram Vishwanath

Summer 2015 IBM T.J. Watson Research Center

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Bruce D'Amora

Summer 2014 AT&T Research

Middletown, NJ, USA

Research intern, Mentors: Lauro Lins and James Klosowski

Summer 2013 Sandia National Laboratories

Albuquerque, NM, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Patricia Crossno

2009 - 2012 **TecGraf / PUC-Rio** 

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research assistant, Mentor: Waldemar Celes

#### **Awards**

2018 SIGMOD Best Demonstration Award

For "Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets Using Urbane".

2018 Pearl Brownstein Doctoral Research Award

For doctoral research that shows the greatest promise, awarded by NYU.

2010-2012 CAPES and Petrobras Fellowships
 Awarded during M.S. studies.

 2006-2009 FINEP and CNPq Fellowships
 Awarded during B.S. studies.

# **Selected Media Coverage**

February 2022 Escuelas y comunidades latinas en Chicago son las más afectadas por la contaminación, según estudio

Univision Chicago 🗗

November 2017 Urban Pulse maps, analyzes use of urban spaces

GCN 🗗

September 2017 Urban Pulse Uses Social Media Data to Show Cities in a New Light

Architectural Digest 🗹

September 2017 New program wants to improve cities with the power of tweets and Flickr uploads

Curbed 🗹

December 2016 Mapping the Shadows of New York City: Every Building, Every Block

The New York Times 🗷

October 2016 Listen to the music of the traffic in the city

The Economist 🗹

#### **Publications**

<u>Underlined name</u>: advised UIC student \*YYYY: paper submitted after joining UIC

#### Under review:

\*2022 A Comparison of Spatiotemporal Visualizations for 3D Urban Analytics
R. Mota, N. Ferreira, J. D. Silva, M. Horga, M. Lage, L. Ceferino, U. R. Alim, E. Sharlin, **F. Miranda**\*\*IEEE VIS 2022 (under review)

\*2022 A Comparative Study of Methods for Visualization of Probability Distributions of Geographical Data <a href="S. Srabanti">S. Srabanti</a>, C. V. de Souza, E. J. da Silva, M. Lage, N. Ferreira, **F. Miranda**The Visual Computer Journal

#### Accepted:

\*2022 Near-fall detection in unexpected slips during over-ground locomotion

S. Wang, **F. Miranda**, Y. Wang, <u>R. Rasheed</u>, T. Bhatt

Sensors (major revision)

\*2022 Urban Rhapsody: Large-scale Visual Exploration of Urban Soundscapes

J. Rulff, **F. Miranda**, M. Hosseini, M. Lage, M. Cartwright, G. Dove, J. P. Bello, C. Silva *Computer Graphics Forum (accepted)* 

\*2022 A Tale of Two Centers: Visual Exploration of Health Disparities in Cancer Care S. Srabanti, M. Tran, V. Achim, D. Fuller, G. Canahuate, **F. Miranda**, G.E. Marai

2022 IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis)

\*2022 CitySurfaces: City-scale Semantic Segmentation of Sidewalks Surfaces

M. Hosseini, F. Miranda, J. Lin, C. Silva

Sustainable Cities and Society (accepted)

- Visualizing Simulation Ensembles of Extreme Weather Events
   C. V. de Souza, P. Luz, M. Cataldi, F. Miranda, M. Lage
   Computers & Graphics (accepted)
- Visualizing Environmental Justice Issues in Urban Areas with a Community Input Approach
   J. Flax-Hatch, S. Srabanti, F. Miranda, A. Sambanis, M. Cailas
   2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium
   Featured on Univision Chicago
- \*2021 Sidewalk Measurements from Satellite Images: Preliminary Findings
  M. Hosseini, I. B. Araujo, H. Yazdanpanah, E. Tokuda, **F. Miranda**, C. Silva, R. M. Cesar Jr

  2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium
- \*2021 COVID-19 EnsembleVis: Visual Analysis of County-level Ensemble Forecast Models

  <u>S. Srabanti</u>, G. E. Marai, **F. Miranda**12th Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare
- \*2021 Transportation Scenario Planning with Graph Neural Network
  A. A. Peregrino, <u>S. Pradhan</u>, Z. Liu, N. Ferreira, **F. Miranda**10th International Workshop on Urban Computing
- UrbanRama: Navigating Cities in Virtual Reality
   S. Chen, F. Miranda, N. Ferreira, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Brenner, C. Defanti, M. Koutsoubis, L. Wilson,
   K. Perlin, C. Silva
   IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (accepted)
- 2020 Urban Mosaic: Visual Exploration of Streetscapes Using Large-scale Image Data **F. Miranda**, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, M. Hosseini, G. Dove, C. T. Silva 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.
- Learning Geo-Contextual Embeddings for Commuting Flow Prediction
   Z. Liu, F. Miranda, W. Xiong, J. Yang, Q. Wang, C. T. Silva
   Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence.
- Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time

  F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva

  IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 3, pp. 1559-1574, Mar 2019.

  Featured on The New York Times
- Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual Analysis of Large Time Series **F. Miranda**, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Mydlarz, J. Salamon, Y. Lockerman, J. Freire, C. T. Silva Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 37, no. 3, pp. 23-35, Jun 2018.
- Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets using Urbane
   H. Doraiswamy, E. Tzirita Zacharatou, F. Miranda, M. Lage, A. Ailamaki, C. T. Silva, J. Freire
   2018 ACM SIGMOD Intl. Conf. on Management of Data Demo.
   Best Demonstration Award
- Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Analysis: A Visual Analytics Perspective
   H. Doraiswamy, J. Freire, M. Lage, F. Miranda, C. T. Silva
   IEEE Computer Graphics and Application, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 26-35, Sept/Oct 2018.
- TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

  F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

  IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 1394-1407, Mar 2018.
- Urban Pulse: Capturing the Rhythm of Cities

  F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, K. Zao, B. Goncalves, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva

  IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 23, no. 1, pp. 791-800, Jan 2017.

  Featured on The Economist, invited to SIGGRAPH 2017 TVCG special session

5th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Models and Technologies for Intelligent Transportation Systems (2017). TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets 2016 F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva Data Systems for Interactive Analysis (DSIA) 2016. 2012 Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes **F. Miranda**, and W. Celes The Visual Computer Journal, vol. 28, no. 10, pp. 1005-1014, Oct 2012. 2011 Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes F. Miranda, and W. Celes 24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011). Illustrative Volume Visualization for Unstructured Meshes Based on Photic Extremum Lines 2011 A. Rocha, **F. Miranda**, and W. Celes 24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011). **Funding** PRESUR: Planning a Resilient and Equitable State Using **Discovery Partners** Fall 2022 - Fall 2023 **Real-time Data** Institute Co-PI, \$125,000 (direct total) **Teaching** University of Illinois at Spring 2022 **CS425: Computer Graphics I** Chicago Undergraduate course. No. of students enrolled: 49. Course page 🗹 University of Illinois at **CS594: Big Data Visualization & Analytics** Fall 2021 Chicago Graduate course. No. of students enrolled: 29. Average student evaluation score: 4.4 / 5.0 (n=25, std. dev.=0.76) Course page 🗹 University of Illinois at Spring 2021 **CS425: Computer Graphics I** Chicago Undergraduate course. No. of students enrolled: 41. Average student evaluation score: 4.03 / 5.0 (n=33, std. dev.=0.98) Course page 🗹 **Advised Students** University of Illinois at 2021 -Ph.D. students (advisor) Chicago Kazi Omar, Marius Horga, Sanjana Srabanti (co-adivising with G. Elisabeta Marai) University of Illinois at 2021 -M.Sc. students (advisor) Chicago Soham Pradhan University of Illinois at 2021 -**Undergraduate students (advisor)** 

Data Visualization Tool for Monitoring Transit Operation and Performance

A. Kurkcu, **F. Miranda**, K. Ozbay, C. T. Silva

2017

Daniel Hodczak, Jayanth Podapati, Reem Sheikh, Rahiya Rasheed

Chicago

2018 -Ph.D. students (mentor) **New York University** 

Zhicheng Liu (CS PhD student at Southeast University, China), Maryam Hosseini (Urban Systems PhD student at Rutgers), Shaoyu Chen (CS PhD student at NYU), João Rulff (CS PhD student at NYU).

**Selected Invited Talks and Presentations** 

**Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Immersive Analytics** April 2022

Online

**Opportunities** The Next Evolution: XR & AEC

**VRAR CHICAGO** 

Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland January 2022

Online

**Urban Initiative Program New York University** 

April 2021 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland Online

Department of Energy Computer Graphics Forum 2021

Department of Energy

**Perspective on Cities** 

**Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational** April 2021

Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil

**Perspective on Cities** Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul

Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational March 2021

Niteroi, RJ, Brazil

Fluminense Federal University

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020

Insights

New Orleans, LA, USA

**Tulane University** 

Insights

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable January 2020

Portland, OR, USA

Portland State University

**Shadows over Time** 

December 2018 **Exploration of Street-Level Images at Scale**  New York City, NY, USA

Pedestrian Movement Technology Showcase at Metro North

**Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale** November 2018

Berlin, Germany

IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)

Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual June 2018

**Analysis of Large Time Series** 

Brno, Czech Republic

EG/VGTC Conference on Visualization (EuroVis)

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2017

Phoenix, AZ, USA

IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)

September 2016 **Visualizing and Exploring Urban Data**  Boston, MA, USA

Data Visualization Summit

**Spatiotemporal Datasets** 

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2016

**Spatiotemporal Datasets** 

Chicago, IL, USA

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis Workshop (DSIA)

#### **Academic Services**

## **Program chair**

• SIBGRAPI (2022)

# **Conference and workshop organization**

- VIS 2021, Local co-chair (2021)
- The Future of Global-Scale Spatial Data Collection and Analyses on Urban (in)Accessibility for People with Disabilities Workshop, Co-chair (2021)

#### **Program committees**

- IEEE VIS Full papers (2022) IEEE VIS Short papers (2019, 2020, 2021)
- EuroVis (2022) Visualization and Data Analysis Conference (2022) SIBGRAPI (2019, 2020, 2021)

#### Editor

• Computers & Graphics (SIBGRAPI 2022 Special Issue)

#### **Grant reviewer**

- NSF reviewer (GRFP, 2022), (CSSI, 2022)
- Center for Transportation, Equity, Decisions and Dollars reviewer (2022) Discovery Partners Institute reviewer (2021)

#### Journal reviewer

- IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics (2020, 2021) IEEE Trans. on Big Data (2020)
- IEEE Trans. on Intelligent Transportation Systems (2021) The Visual Computer Journal (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022) Transportation Research Record Journal (2020) International Journal of Geo-Information (2021)

#### **Conference reviewer**

- IEEE VIS (2018, 2019, 2020, 2021) Sibgrapi (2018, 2019, 2020, 2021)
- VLDB (2021) WWW (2021) International Conference on Pattern Recognition (2020, 2021, 2022)

# **University Services**

## **Department committees**

- Faculty Search Committee (2022)
- Graduate Admission Committee (2020, 2021)

## Reviewer

• Provost's Graduate Research Award reviewer (2020)

#### **WCP** committees

• Carla Floricel (2021) • Md Nafiul Alam Nipu (2021) • Andrew Wentzel (2021) • Muhammad Abdul Wahhab (2021)

#### **Master's project committees**

●Parikshit Solunke (2021) ● Pavana Doddi (2021)

## **Professional Memberships**

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM). Brazilian Computer Society (Sociedade Brasileira de Computação, SBC).